<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-06-15T14:06:45-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">B.T. Carter</title><subtitle>A website dedicated to all things neuroscience, neuroimaging, tutorials, graduate school, and the endless wheel of scientific inquiry. © 2019 Benjamin Carter.</subtitle><author><name>Benjamin T. Carter</name></author><entry><title type="html">Working with research participants</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/10/17/interviewingParticipants.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Working with research participants" /><published>2019-10-17T23:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-10-17T23:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/10/17/interviewingParticipants</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/10/17/interviewingParticipants.html">&lt;p&gt;I have been involved in basic science research now for almost a decade (that makes me feel older than it should). The first was the addiction lab at BYU, which utilized rodent models to investigate involvement of reward centers in the brain in addiction. The second was the cardiothoracic research lab at the University of Virginia, which used the porcine model to investigate new methods for lung transplantation. The third (and current lab) is the BYU eye-tracking lab, headed by Dr. Steven Luke. This lab was quite different from the others. Instead of utilizing animals, our research requires humans to willingly participate in our research. Successful experimentation no longer requires good surgical techniques, nor can comfort be administered in the form of an opiod or paralytic. It requires soft skills in order to interact with a participant in order to build repoire and help them feel comfortable. This adds a social aspect to my science that was absent from my previous research.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my short time as a graduate student, I have observed these skills to be somewhat lacking among researchers, particularly those just getting started. This is not surprising as much of this can only be mastered through practiced experience. A good mentor who can train, observe and critique is especially helpful. I just got thrown right into middle of things while a graduate student. Luckily for me, my service as a proselyting missionary (imagine going door to door trying to talk to people about religion all day) and my rudimentary training in medical interviews prior to graduate school has made working with people a less than foreign concept. This has made the transition from animals to humans less awkward, though I still make a great deal of mistakes.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I present here are some thoughts (in no particular order) on how to become a better human researcher, especially for those who have not recieved any training in human research methods (e.g. any non-clinical neuroscience or physiology program).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tips&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Find an expert:&lt;/em&gt; Having an expert to observe and train under is incredibly useful. If you are in a lab with leaders who are hands-off or uninvolved then do not be afraid to ask to watch them do it first. Ask them to allow you to practice on them once or twice just so you can get a feel for things. Ask for feedback often.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Know your protocol/tests:&lt;/em&gt; I won't say memorize your protocol (it might be long enough to be impractical) but certainly know it well enough to make executing it second nature. You should refer to your notes to double check yourself, not to tell you what to do next. This allows you to proceed through a participant interview or testing fluidly and comfortably. If you are comfortable the participant will be comfortable (or at least less uncomfortable)!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Be prepared:&lt;/em&gt; Take time prior to the participant interview to prepare the room and set out all the materials you will need, whether that's a lab manual, test forms, stimuli, or digital protocol. This will help you by giving you visual cues to remind you what to do and what order (making for a fluid interaction), as well as present yourself as a professional to your participant. This builds repoire.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Be professional:&lt;/em&gt; Manners maketh man. Present yourself as a professional. Do not show up in sweat pants and a t-shirt. Wear clothes that set a professional tone. Consider the participant's cultural predisposition as well. Try to make them comfortable. Your explicit t-shirt may be funny, but it may give your participant a reason not to trust you or think the research is a big joke like you.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Be water:&lt;/em&gt; One of Bruce Lee's maxims, it certainly applies to human research. While you should stick to the script of your protocol, the only thing that is certain in research is that no single trial or experiment perfectly conforms to the protocol. Sometimes it is because of the participant, e.g. they show up late to an appointment, or there is some unforseen medical complication. At times it is expedient for you to leave the scripted protocal behind and ask questions not in the script as a means of clarifying some point. Do not let this fluster you. When something unscripted happens just roll with it and document it. No matter who wrote the protocol, there is no way it will address every single contingency. No man or woman is all knowing enough to create such a document. Protocols delineate default action, but they should not limit you as a researcher, so long as you document what happens and what you did.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Benjamin Carter</name></author><summary type="html">I have been involved in basic science research now for almost a decade (that makes me feel older than it should). The first was the addiction lab at BYU, which utilized rodent models to investigate involvement of reward centers in the brain in addiction. The second was the cardiothoracic research lab at the University of Virginia, which used the porcine model to investigate new methods for lung transplantation. The third (and current lab) is the BYU eye-tracking lab, headed by Dr. Steven Luke. This lab was quite different from the others. Instead of utilizing animals, our research requires humans to willingly participate in our research. Successful experimentation no longer requires good surgical techniques, nor can comfort be administered in the form of an opiod or paralytic. It requires soft skills in order to interact with a participant in order to build repoire and help them feel comfortable. This adds a social aspect to my science that was absent from my previous research.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Searching for a postdoctoral position</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/06/06/looking_for_postdoc.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Searching for a postdoctoral position" /><published>2019-06-06T23:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-06-06T23:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/06/06/looking_for_postdoc</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/06/06/looking_for_postdoc.html">I should have known that something was up that morning when Dr. Luke sent me a text message asking if I was in the lab. Usually its the otherway around. That's when he told me about a postdoctoral opportunity in Davis, California. The only catch? I was going to complete my dissertation in six months instead of eighteen. Talk about stress and anticipation! We're currently trying to arrange for an interview some time later this summer so I can learn more about it and make a better decision about going there.

In the meantime my wife and I have been online trying to do some digital scouting. From what we can tell, the cost of living is incredibly high, as much as 15-20% higher. Most of that is due to the cost of rent (or a mortgage, though we can't afford a mortgage). Our current residence would cost about $2,500 a month, a 100% increase, if it were located in Davis. How am I supposed to support a family on $50,000? We'll figure that out I suppose.</content><author><name>Benjamin Carter</name></author><summary type="html">I should have known that something was up that morning when Dr. Luke sent me a text message asking if I was in the lab. Usually its the otherway around. That's when he told me about a postdoctoral opportunity in Davis, California. The only catch? I was going to complete my dissertation in six months instead of eighteen. Talk about stress and anticipation! We're currently trying to arrange for an interview some time later this summer so I can learn more about it and make a better decision about going there.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Site Update</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/06/05/update.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Site Update" /><published>2019-06-05T23:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-06-05T23:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/06/05/update</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/06/05/update.html">&lt;h2&gt;What happened?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have reorganized the site so tutorials do not post directly to the main page but now are added as a separate collection of documents. You will find them under the Tutorials tab in the top right-hand side of the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also altered the site domain. It was once listed under bc-brains.com but is now renamed something more generic, benjamintcarter.org. This was a long overdue update as I realized I need a site that was a bit more generic in its naming convention so it was more appropriately connected the site mission. The name bc-brains was starting to appear both cliché and limiting. I'm going to start looking for post-doctoral positions in the near future and will probably use this site to post material related to my work, classes I teach, and other random things related to my interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some additional updates in the future. I may reorganize the tutorials again and break it off into a subdomain once it gets sufficiently large. Class information will also be added as its own subdomain as well once that material is posted (this is probably imminent).
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Benjamin Carter</name></author><summary type="html">What happened?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Data Structure in NeuroImaging</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/03/28/bids.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Data Structure in NeuroImaging" /><published>2019-03-28T23:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-03-28T23:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/03/28/bids</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/03/28/bids.html">&lt;h2&gt;The BIDS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neuroimaging projects produce a lot of data. For example, one of my recent projects produced an average of 3 GB of data per participant after the analysis was completed (and there were over 40 participants, which means there was about 120 GB of data). And that was for one functional analysis. Once I complete the structural, DTI, and resting state analyses I expect the data will grow exponentially, and this is for just one study. Imaging how much data I will be dealing with after a decade of research.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Keeping this data organized is time consuming, a little complicated, and is not standardized between labs, until recently. Gorgolewski, et al. (2016) has proposed a standardized method for researchers to implement called the &lt;i&gt;brain imaging data structure&lt;/i&gt; (BIDS). It looks something like this.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.nature.com/lw926/nature-assets/sdata/2016/sdata201644/images_hires/sdata201644-f1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Figure 1, example of BIDS from Gorgolewski, et al 2016.&quot;&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 1 from Gorgolewski, et al 2016. An example of a BIDS formatted dataset&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'll save myself summarizing the paper. It's fairly simple so if you want to learn more about it just checkout the link listed below. The above figure does a decent job of capturing the idea. Essentially, DICOMs (and other forms of raw data) are kept in a separate directory from your processed data. Derived data (i.e. the data you produce during preprocessing and analysis like BRIK and HEAD files in AFNI) is then organized within a study directory by subject, then within a directory for that data type.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another layer of organization can be found in file naming syntax. Files are named such that if they are moved from their home directory they can still be identified. The naming convention is as follows: &lt;code&gt;participantID_imagingSequence&lt;/code&gt;. Additional files are included for metadata such as participant lists, and lists of data types with descriptions. These are usually formated as tab-delimited files.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information I really do suggest reading the original article (see below). It should only take about 20 minutes!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gorgolewski, K. J., Auer, T., Calhoun, V. D., Craddock, R. C., Das, S., Duff, E. P., ... &amp; Handwerker, D. A. (2016). &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/sdata201644&quot;&gt;The brain imaging data structure, a format for organizing and describing outputs of neuroimaging experiments&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;i&gt;Scientific Data, 3&lt;/i&gt;, 160044.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Benjamin Carter</name></author><summary type="html">The BIDS</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">SfN 2018, San Diego, California</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/11/06/sfn2018.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SfN 2018, San Diego, California" /><published>2018-11-06T22:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-11-06T22:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/11/06/sfn2018</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2018/11/06/sfn2018.html">&lt;h2&gt;Society for Neuroscience Annual Conference&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Sunday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annual Society for Neuroscience conference is here! It got kicked off yesterday but Sunday was my first day as Saturday was my traveling day. I flew out of SLC in the afternoon at 3:00 PM and arrived in San Diego an hour later local time. I took a taxi to my hotel (which amounted to highway robbery), checked in and got settled. It was already fairly late in the day at that point so I went for a run. Turns out Sunny San Diego has a bit of a dark side. I was running near the University of California at San Diego Medical Center. Found multiple piles of garbage strewn about the street, feces, and evidence of multiple encampments. Apparently California really does have a homelessness problem. After that I went back to the hotel and did not leave for the rest of the night. I was far enough from downtown that walking would have been a long affair and taking a taxi would have been costly. So I called it a day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dynamic interaction of vision and eye movements was the first minisymposium I attended and it was a bit out in left field. The methods most of the investigators used were focused around electrophysiological recordings in various animal models. Not exactly what I generally investigate. After that I caught the tail end of a talk on Multiscale Modeling of Brain Disease by W.W Lytton, from State University of New York State. He focused on using computer based models to understand and simulate neurological function at the level of the cell, circuit, and brain. I wonder if this could be used in the classroom (maybe for an advanced neuroscience class) to teach principles of neuronal circuitry. It would certainly be a better alternative to just discussing the concepts in class and using theoretical questioning to probe understanding. I think it could be interesting.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that I attended a presidential lecture on Neural Data Science: Accelerating the Experiment-Analysis-Theory Cycle in Large-Scale Neuroscience, by Liam Paninski. That was interesting. His talk centered around the open neuroscience movement, and one of his projects in particular which is focused on finding new ways to make optigenetic and microscopy available to the broader scientific community through appropriate data filtration and compression. He also made a broader plea for more students to seek training in data science (which I agree with). Neuroscience is on the edge of a new era in terms of reproducibility and data analysis. Thanks to the internet and increased local computing power and the availability of remote computing we can now conduct studies that were impossible before. However this data will go to waste if there is not anyone to look at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Scribbles from other meetings&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neural data science – We need more neural data scientists, people who can speak the language of neuroscience and statistics.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Is he using LaTex?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;An Internation Laboratory for Systems and Computational Neuroscience, Neuron&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Bottle necks: How to reconcile large datasets from disparate modalities?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Ways to do so - filtering out noise, making dataset a little coarser so it requires less memory (though I do not think this is completely necessary as memory capacity and computing power are increasing at an exponential rate).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Monday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nanosymposium on vision and eye movements was electrifying, and by that was comprised primarily of electrophysiological studies of the superior colliculus. While not my primary interest, I attended because it was somewhat related to my field of research. Unfortunately the talk that drew my initial attention ended up being a no show (which is something that I would think would never happen at an international conference). In lieu of that speaker the chairman just had us take a short break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;David Kopf lecture on Neuroethics: When is an adolescent an adult? Implications for Justice Policy by B. J. Casey&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Healthy development is a fundamental right. Declaration of the rights of the child, League of Nations and UN. (Not sure this is a right but certainly a noble aim)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Relevant Court Cases&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;ol&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Roper v. Simmons (2005): No death penalty for minors.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Graham v. Florida (2010)&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Miller v. Alabama (2012)&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Montgomery v. Louisiana (2016)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Cohen, 2016, Temple Law review&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Key questions&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;ul&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;When do cognitive, emotional, social abilities reach maturity?&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;What are the signs?&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Does the law align with these markers?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Whack a mole, asymptote at 16-17, Durston 2002, Casey &amp; Caudle, 2013&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Cognitive ability reaches maturity apparently around 16-17 years old.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Sommerville et al 2011 JoCN, Smiling cues, teens are more impulsive to positive social cues.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Adolescents are more reactive to negative cues. Influence of negative social cues, Dreyfuss, 2014 Developmental Neuroscience&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Most crime committed in groups, National Crime victimization survey, 2014&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Adolescents with a peer perform worse, crash paradigm, Chein, 2010&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Steinburg, Cauffman, 2009, American Psychologist, Cognitive, Psychosocial maturity&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;So cognitive abilities mature at about 16-17 while other social and emotional abilities finish sometime in the late teens and early twenties.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Somerville, 2016, Neuron, Signatures of Brain Maturity.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;However, young children do not show the same degree of difference from adults that teens do so this may be due to a developmentally driven imbalance of systems rather than a lag in development.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Functional conectome becomes more distinct with age, Kauffman 2017, Nat Neuro&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Young Adult courts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Intersubject correlation for social and non-social videos in the default mode network, Mark Straccia, UCLA&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Potential DMN causes&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;ul&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Is the DMN involved in the language, narrative, social tasks for video?&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;duth 2016&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;husson 2017 TICS - narratives&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Story comprehension - lerner 2015, J neuro&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Ames 2015 J cog neuro&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Did you account for eye movements or engagement?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Apparently saw greatest activation for non-language social interactions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Thinking ahead: Using ECoG to map the spatiotemporal dynamics of prediction during natural language comprehension, Amy Price, Uri Hasson, Princeton&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;ECoG - electrocorticography (electrodes in epilepsy patients)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Computed cloze probability for words&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Sorted words into groups (high v. low) using linguistic factors&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;High predictability - Higher cortical regions were recruited up to 200 msec faster, indicating anticipatory processing was occuring.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Benjamin Carter</name></author><summary type="html">Society for Neuroscience Annual Conference</summary></entry></feed>